<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An introduction to pietie and humanitie containing, first, a short catechisme for vnderstanding the grounds of religion: secondly, certaine briefe and effectuall rules for life and conuersation. Penned specially for the vse of the poore children of Christ's Hospitall in London: but generallie may serue for any other that would be instructed therein. By Gregorie Brovvne.</title>
            <author>Browne, Gregory.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3908.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851448</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16722</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16722)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1657:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An introduction to pietie and humanitie containing, first, a short catechisme for vnderstanding the grounds of religion: secondly, certaine briefe and effectuall rules for life and conuersation. Penned specially for the vse of the poore children of Christ's Hospitall in London: but generallie may serue for any other that would be instructed therein. By Gregorie Brovvne.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Gregory.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 50+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. A[llde] for E. Weauer dwelling at the great North-dore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all after page 50.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christ's Hospital (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An</hi> INTRODVCTION TO PIETIE AND HV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie: containing, <hi>Firſt,</hi> A SHORT CATECHISME for vnderſtanding the grounds <hi>of Religion: Secondly,</hi> CERTAINE BRIEFE AND EF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall rules for life and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PENNED SPECIALLY FOR the vſe of the poore children of Chriſts <hi>Hoſpitall in London:</hi> But generallie may ſerue for any other <hi>that would be inſtructed</hi> therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GREGORIE BROVVNE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 19,</bibl>
               <p>The law of the Lord is perfect, conuerting th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119.</bibl>
               <p>The entrance into thy word ſheweth light, and giueth wiſedome to the ſimple.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>E. A.</hi> for <hi>Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und Weauer</hi> dwelling at the <hi>great North-dore of Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL GENTLEMEN, LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of learning, Piety and Charity, the Gouernours of Chriſts Hoſpitall in London, foſter fathers of the poore Orphans, and helpleſſe Children there releeued; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He giuer of all goodneſſe, Right worſhipfull, hauing, promiſed that the beſt good things, being firſt ſought and preferred, the ſecond <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note> neceſſary for life ſhall neuer faile; I haue accordingly endeuored to my poore talent, and leaſure, together with others, to wiſh the ſpeciall good of theſe poore Children, which by God his prouidence are caſt vpon your louing care and fatherly protection: deſiring that in priuate euen from their infancy, they might be ſeaſoned with ſome taſte of piety and humanity, which might make for their better good when they are
<pb facs="tcp:16722:3"/> in publike to be further trained vp in the practiſe of Religion and Arts: for man new born is like a wild Aſſes coult; &amp; folly is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in the heart of a child, vntil by edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation &amp; diſcipline it be made fit to beare &amp; bring forth better fruit. If any good ſhal come hereof to that end; I haue my deſire, as the chiefeſt good which I know is here intended in their foſtering and educating in this Chriſtian gouernment; which hath and ſhall cauſe many prayers and praiſes to God for your worſhips, that you may be had in an euerlasting remembrance, and the whole benefit in the end to redound vnto you and others, who haue ruled with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, &amp; diſtributed with cheerefulnes; when God ſhall haue the glory, Religion the credit, our King the honor, the Citie and whole State the profit, and your ſelues comfort of conſcience, &amp; bleſſing of peace and plentie, which the God of peace and loue graunt vnto you all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all Chriſtian duty, <hi>G. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:3"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y chiefe deſire and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in this (like the poore Bee that gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of diuers plants, and borroweth of ſundrie mens labours, to contriue a worke profitable for orhers) hath beene to benefit my ſelfe and family, but cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe poore children with whom I am conuerſant in my poore calling. If God the giuer of all goodneſſe, vouchſafe his bleſſing to it, for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate or publike good, I haue my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; and with my further endeuour and prayer to God, will not ceaſe to ſeeke and wiſh the ſame ſtill; ſo far as the quality of a Chriſtian calling, health, &amp; poore abilitie will permit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in prayer. G. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Scripture">
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PLACES OF SCRIPTVRE ſhewing the Antiquity, and neceſſity of teaching and catechiſing of youth &amp; families; both priuate and publike, euen</hi> from the example of the Fathers of the firſt ages of the world, vnto the times of the Primi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iue ſtate of the Church.</head>
            <p>AND in proceſſe of time it came to paſſe, that <hi>Kaine</hi> brought an oblation to the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4, 3,</note> Lord of the fruit of the ground. And <hi>Habel</hi> alſo himſelfe brought of the firſt fruit of his ſheepe, and of the fat of them: and the Lord had reſpect vnto <hi>Habel</hi> and to his offring: <hi>For</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 11. 4.</note> by faith he offered a greater ſacrifice then <hi>Kain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Henoch</hi> walked with God after he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneſis 5, 22</note> 
               <hi>Methuſhelah</hi> 300. yeares, and begate ſonnes and daughters. So all the dayes of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> were 365. yeares. And God tooke him away becauſe he walked with God, and had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him; but without faith it is impoſſible to <note place="margin">Heb, 11, 5,</note> pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Lamech</hi> liued 182. yeares, and begate a ſonne, and called his name <hi>Noah,</hi> ſaying, this <note place="margin">Geneſis, 5, 28</note> ſame ſhall comfort vs concerning our workes,
<pb facs="tcp:16722:4"/> and ſorow of our hands, as touching the earth which the Lord hath curſed. But <hi>Noath</hi> found <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſ 6. 8.</note> grace in the eies of God, being a iuſt man and vpright in his time, walking with God: and was made heyre of the righteouſneſſe which is by faith. And the Lord ſaid vnto <hi>Noah,</hi> enter <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 7.</note> thou &amp; all thy houſe into the arke: for thee haue <note place="margin">Geneſ. 7. 1.</note> I found righteous before me in this age &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For I knowe that <hi>Abraham</hi> will commaund his ſonnes and his houſhold after him, that they <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 19.</note> may keepe the way of the Lord, to doe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 9.</note> and iudgment, that the Lord may bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Abraham,</hi> that which hee hath ſpoken vnto him. Then ſaid <hi>Iacob</hi> to his houſhold, and to all that were with him; put away the ſtrange Gods <note place="margin">Geneſ. 35. 2.</note> that are among you, and cleanſe your ſelues, and <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 21.</note> change your garments, for wee will riſe and goe to Bethel, to ſacrifice vnto God, who heard mee in my tribulation; and they did ſo: &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And when your children aske you what ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 26.</note> is this you keepe; then you ſhall ſay, it is the ſacrifice of the Lords Paſſeouer &amp;c. And thou ſhalt ſhew thy Son in that day ſaying, this is done becauſe of that which the Lord did vnto <note place="margin">Exod. 13. 8.</note> me, when I came out of Aegypt.</p>
            <p>And theſe words which I commaund thee <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 6.</note> this day, ſhall be in thine heart, and thou ſhalt <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 9.</note> rehearſe them continually vnto thy children,
<pb facs="tcp:16722:5"/> and ſhalt talke of them when thou tarieſt in <note place="margin">Deut. 11. 19. 20. 21.</note> thine houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way; and when thou lieſt down, &amp; when thou riſeſt vp. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if it ſeeme euill vnto you to ſerue the Lord, chuſe you this day whom yee will ſerue: but I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord. <note place="margin">Ioſu. 24. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The continuance of this in the ages inſuing, is verified in the practiſe of <hi>Samuel,</hi> the 19. chapter, the 19. 20. 21. 22. 23. and 24. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19 18</note> As alſo 140. yeares after this time in the times of <hi>Elias,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> moſt troubleſome <note place="margin">2. Kings 1. 1. 3. 4. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. 8.</note> times, yet was this practiſed then in a moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and propheticall manner. [I will open my mouth in a Parable: I will declare high ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of olde] which we haue heard and known, &amp; <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 2.</note> our fathers haue told vs; we will not hide them from their children, but declare them to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations to come.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Salomon</hi> my ſonne, know the God of thy father, &amp; ſerue him with a perfect heart, <note place="margin">1. Chro. 21. 9.</note> and with a willing mind.</p>
            <p>For I was my fathers ſonne, tender and deare <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 3.</note> in the ſight of my mother; when he taught mee and ſaid vnto me, let thine heart hold faſt my words: &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Propheſie which his mother alſo taught <note place="margin">Prou. 31. 1.</note> him: What my ſonne, and what the ſonne of my wombe, &amp;c. giue not thy ſtrength vnto wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;
<pb facs="tcp:16722:5"/> nor thy waies, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Teach a childe in the trade of his wayes, and <note place="margin">Prou. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.</note> when he is olde he ſhall not depart from it.</p>
            <p>Precept muſt be vpon precept, precept vpon precept, line vnto line, heere a little and there <note place="margin">Eſay. 28. 10</note> a little, as the Prophet ſpeaketh in another kinde. <note place="margin">Luke. 2. 42. &amp; 22. 23. Marke. 10. 15. 16, Pſal, 78. Matth. 16. 15. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The example of our bleſſed Sauiour through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Euangeliſts, is moſt pregnant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to be conſidered in this kinde, opening his mouth in parables, and declaring hid ſentences of olde.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Philip</hi> ran thither, and heard him reade the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> and ſaid, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt <note place="margin">Act. 8. 30.</note> thou what thou readeſt? And he ſaid, how can I, except I had a guide? And he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And you fathers prouoke not your children <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 4.</note> to wrath, but bring them vp in inſtruction and information of the Lord.</p>
            <p>For it ſhalbe in the laſt times, ſaith God, I <note place="margin">Ioel. 2. 28. Act. 2. 17. 1. Theſſ. 5. 18.</note> will powre out of my ſpirit vpon all fleſh: and your ſonnes and your daughters ſhall propheſie.</p>
            <p>Quench not the ſpirit, deſpiſe not propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (preaching and teaching.)</p>
            <p>Therefore leauing the doctrines of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings <note place="margin">Hebr. 5. 12. Hebr. 6. 3. 1. Cor. 3. 1. 2.</note> of Chriſt: let vs be led forward vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not laying againe the foundation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb facs="tcp:16722:6"/> from dead workes, and of faith toward God, of the doctrine of Baptiſme, and laying on of hands, and of the reſurrection from the dead, and of eternall iudgement.</p>
            <p>Let him that is inſtructed in the word, make <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 6.</note> him that hath inſtructed him partaker of all his goods.</p>
            <p>The inſtructers of yong Chriſtians in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, were called Catechiſts; and thoſe inſtructed, Catechumenine, &amp; hearers, or young hearers; and their teachers, teachers of the hearers. Theſe appeare to be in the times of the holy Fathers, ſhortly after the Apoſtles age; as <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Auſtin, Ierome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>God Almighty the giuer of euery good and perfect gift, reuine and continue it in this decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning age, to his glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:6"/>
            <head>A PRAYER TO BE SAID before Catechiſing, as followeth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, which openeſt and none ſhutteth, open our eyes, and touch our harts, that wee may ſee and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the wonderfull things of thy Law, that our minds being inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with true knowledge, and our hearts confirmed with vnfeined faith wee may more and more bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Image of thy Sonne againe, to ſerue thee in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, keeping faith and a good conſcience, vntill wee attaine to the end of our faith, euen the ſaluation of our ſoules, through Chriſt our Lord and only Sauiour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:16722:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16722:7"/>
            <head>A SHORT CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TECHISME FOR THE Elder ſort of the Children of Chriſts Hoſpitall in London.</head>
            <head type="sub">To be vſed of them after the ſmall Catechiſme which is to be taught and learned of euery Child, as is appointed by authority.</head>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EING we are yet to ſpeake of God the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne good; and of his word our guide to true happyneſſe; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto vs what God is?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> God is an eternall Spirit, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, holy, Iuſt and mercifull, being an infinit perfection; whoſe being is of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, giuing being to all, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of time or end of dayes, one in eſſence, and thrée diſtinct perſones, one mighty na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16722:8"/> be they; the Father, Sonne, and Holy-Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Who is the Creator and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the world?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This one almighty God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136, 5,</note> Son, and holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why were the Heauens, Angels, and celeſtiall bodies made?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> For the glory of God, and ſeruice of man: as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>the heauens declare the glory of God:</hi> and the Apoſtle <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</note> ſaith, <hi>the Angels are all miniſtring ſpirits</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>for their ſakes that ſhall be heires of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>But ſome Angels are tempters and hurters of mankinde.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe are Angels which kept not their firſt eſtate of truth and holineſſe, but through pride againſt God and mallice to men, fell as ſtarres from Heauen: being ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aunderers of God, and enimies to men, called the diuell and his Angels, reſerued <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Iude</hi> 6.</note> in euerlaſting chaines vnder darkeneſſe, vnto the Iudgement of the great day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Amongſt all the creatures, which is the chiefeſt then?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Man being conſidered in Chriſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. 5.</note> reſtored to grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16722:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe God hath indued him <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 6.</note> with knowledge, righteouſneſſe, and true holyneſſe, and giuen him reaſon to diſcerne betweene good and euill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What is the chiefeſt end of mans creation?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſerue and glorifie God their <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 43. 7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11. 12.</note> Creator.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What rule hath God left vnto vs, how he would be ſerued?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> His holy Law, firſt written in the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the law. Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7.</note> hart and giuen by God, conſiſting of ten Commaundements in two Tables.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Deuide them.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the firſt foure, which is the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut.</hi> 6. 45. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22 37.</note> firſt Table, is taught our dutie towards God. In the latter ſixe, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table, is contained our dutie to our <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 39 <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 18.</note> neighbour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Rehearſe them.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hee out of the Land of Aegypt, out of the houſe of bondage, thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me. Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Shew me the ſenſe of euery Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, particularly.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1 In the firſt Commandement is ſet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16722:9"/> downe whom we ſhould worſhip, that is, God only and alone. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 In the ſecond, how we ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him: namely according to his word in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math,</hi> 15. 9, <hi>Deut,</hi> 4, 15, <hi>Act,</hi> 7, 29,</note> ſpirit and truth: without repreſentations.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In the third, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end wherefore we ought to worſhip him, that his name may be hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, his kingdome inlarged, and his bleſſed will accompliſhed in all, and ouer <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit,</hi> 9, 12. <hi>Eſay,</hi> 65, 16,</note> all by his word.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In the fourth, The time and meanes which the Lord hath appointed for his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod,</hi> 31, 1, <hi>Cor,</hi> 16, 2</note> worſhip and ſeruice, being the Sabbath day, The Preaching of the Word, admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, prayers, and prayſes. Which foure precepts are the firſt Table, containing our dutie toward God in hallowing his name, In ſeeking his kingdome, and learning his will.</p>
               <p n="5">5 In the fifth, which is the firſt of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table, containing our duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our neighbours, God taketh order for the duties of Inferiours towards their Superiours and Elders, and of the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit,</hi> 20, 9, <hi>Rom,</hi> 13, 1. 2,</note> to their Inferiours.</p>
               <p n="6">6 In the ſixth, of the ſafety of our brothers life; that ciuill ſociety and peace may bée
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16722:9"/> maintained among men. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 3 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 15. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 20. 2 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 In the ſeuenth, of his wife, that chaſt wedlocke and holy conuerſation might bee preſerued, and a holy ſeed continued.</p>
               <p n="8">8 In the eight, of his goods, that true dealing, faithfull labour in our calling, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4, 6.</note> contented minds with our portion, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God, and helpefull furtherance to our brethren may bee practiſed.</p>
               <p n="9">9 In the ninth, of his good name, that truth in word, in witnes, in report, may bée <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 16 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 22</note> exerciſed among men, for the preſeruing of their good names and eſtimation.</p>
               <p n="10">10 In the tenth, is forbidden the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée of ſinne againſt any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23.</note> namely the luſt and motion to ſinne, aſwell as the conſent and deed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Is there preſcribed in the Law a perfect rule of righteouſneſſe?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yea verily, though there be in vs <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 12. 14</note> no ability to performe the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>How commeth that to paſſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man was created perfect?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Through the ſin and tranſgreſſion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 17.</note> of our firſt Parents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Did not that ſinne reſt in A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am alone?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, but it did flow from him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16722:10"/> vnto all mankinde. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 5. 14. 18.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What fruits doth it bring forth in vs?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nothing but ſin, in thought, word and déed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What puniſhment is due to ſin?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Eternall death and damnation. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om.</hi> 6. 12.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>How come we to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the law. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 20.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Whereunto ſerueth this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To humble vs and caſt vs downe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 37.</note> in the ſight and acknowledgement of our owne miſerie: and to bring vs to Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>How is it poſſible for man to be ſaued in this miſerie?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By faith in Chriſt Ieſus, the Son <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 12.</note> of God, the promiſed ſéede of the woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Where is this ſauing knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus briefely ſet downe for vs?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the Articles of the Créed, being <note place="margin">Of faith</note> twelue in number</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Repeat them with the ſenſe of euery one.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1 <hi>I beleeue in God, the Father almighty,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. 6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>maker of Heauen and Earth,</hi> the firſt perſon in Trinitie, maker and gouernor of all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16722:10"/> things in Heauen and in Earth, viſible and inuiſible.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Son our Lord,</hi> the ſecond perſon in Trinitie, who is our King, to gouerne and defend vs, our Prieſt and Prophet, to offer for vs, to teach vs his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 4 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. 17.</note> fathers will.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Which was conceaued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi>
                  </hi> ſhewing the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4.</note> of his pure conception and bleſſed birth taking our nature vpon him without ſin, by faith in whom our nature i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſanctified.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>He ſuffered vnder <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, dead and buried, &amp;c.</hi> which ſheweth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53. 4. 5 <hi>Marke.</hi> 14. 3 <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13.</note> his painefull paſſion, infinit ſuffering, and bitter death, for our ſins, performing moſt abſolute obedience to God for vs.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>The third day he roſe againe from the dead;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 25.</note> which ſheweth his victory after death, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againe for our iuſtification to life.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>He aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth at the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 24. 5 <hi>Marke.</hi> 16. 1</note> 
                  <hi>right hand of God the Father almighty;</hi> which ſheweth of his aſcention and exaltation in glory, hauing all power in Heauen and in Earth giuen him of his father.</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>From thence he ſhal come to iudge the quicke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>and the dead;</hi> which ſheweth of his ſecond glorious appearing in Iudgement, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16722:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16722:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16722:12"/> of all things. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heſſ.</hi> 4. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 25. 31.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt,</hi> the third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Trinity; God equall with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h.</hi> 28. 19 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11.</note> and Sonne, ſanctifier of all the elect people of God.</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>The holy Catholike Church, the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints,</hi> which doe communicate with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſ.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19.</note> Chriſt, and one with another in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of faith and bond of loue.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>The forgiuenes of ſinnes,</hi> belonging to all <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 31. 34. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oh.</hi> 1. 9.</note> the true members of the Church, who only haue peace with God.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>The reſurrection of the body,</hi> from death <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. 26 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uel.</hi> 20. 12.</note> and corruption, to immortalitie, both of good and bad.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>The life euerlaſting,</hi> for the godly, reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all fulnes of ioy and bleſſednes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor</hi> 5. 1, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſ.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſ.</hi> 19. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atth.</hi> 25. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uel.</hi> 14. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> with God and his holy Angels: and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting woe and torments for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before the throne of God, for euer and euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>How many principall parts are theſe Articles of the faith to be drawne to?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Vnto foure principall heads.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Which be they?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, our faith in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Creator.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in God the Son, the Redéemer.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16722:12"/>
               <p> Thirdly, in God the holy Ghoſt, the Sanctifier.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, of the Church, the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints, to whom forgiuenes of ſins, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 36.</note> bleſſed reſurrection, and euerlaſting life and glorie appertaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why ſay you,</hi> I beleeue in God, <hi>and not rather, in Gods, ſeing you make mention of three; the Father, Sonne, and Spirit?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe there is but one true and euerliuing God, reuealed vnto vs in thrée <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 7.</note> perſons, in whom my faith is ſtaied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why do you ſay, <hi>I beleeue in God,</hi> and not rather, I beleeue a God?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To declare that I put my truſt and confidence in him, for the Diuels and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 19.</note> beleeue there is a God, but doe not put their truſt and confidence in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why ſay you, <hi>I beleeue,</hi> and not rather, we beleeue?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe I muſt bée ſaued by mine <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 4.</note> owne faith, and not by the faith of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What is true faith which ſaueth vs?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is a firme perſwaſion of the mercies of God purchaſed by our Lord <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 38. 3</note> Ieſus Chriſt being the foundation of our hope and ſight of things inuiſible:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16722:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>How muſt we attaine to this true faith, and how is it increaſed?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the ſpirit of God, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our hearts by the hearing and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om.</hi> 1. 3.</note> of Gods Word, receauing the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and prayer, aſſuring vs that we are within the Couenant of grace reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Now you haue ſhewed that the Word of God, the Sacraments and prayer, ſtrengthen faith: ſhew what is Prayer.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Prayer is a lifting vp of the minde, <note place="margin">Of prayer.</note> and powring out of the heart before God, by the motion of his Spirit, in the name of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 18. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 13. <hi>Iames.</hi> 4. 3.</note> Ieſus Chriſt his ſon, crauing things néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; giuing thanks for benefits receaued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Is there any preſcript forme of Prayer left vs in the holy Scriptures?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, that which our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath taught, and is called <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> containing all heauenly wiſdome in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 2.</note> that kind, conſiſting of ſixe petitions, and a concluſion, as followeth, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>To whom muſt wee pray, and in whoſe name?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To God only, the Father, Sonne, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ohn</hi> 16. 23.</note>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16722:13"/> and holy Ghoſt, in the name of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why do we then name the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The word <hi>Father,</hi> in this place is not taken perſonally, but eſſentially, for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude.</hi> 20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 34.</note> in the action of true prayer, the holy Ghoſt is the firſt Mouer, the Son the Mediator, the Father gratiouſly hearing, returneth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 24.</note> an anſwere in due time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why muſt we pray to the Father in the name of his Son Mediator?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe God being diſpleaſed for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 10.</note> ſinne, we can haue no acceſſe vnto him, but by the meanes of Chriſt our Aduocate, in whom he is well pleaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why muſt we pray by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the holy Ghoſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 18.</note> vs that God is our Father, and alſo teacheth vs how to pray, and what to pray for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What things are to be obſerued of vs in prayer?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, before the action of prayer; 1. We <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17.</note> muſt truly repent vs of our ſinnes, and hartely purpoſe to amend.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In the action of prayer, 1. We muſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:14"/> haue faith in God through Chriſt. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mes</hi> 1, 6, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arke,</hi> 11, 24 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atth,</hi> 5. 44. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> 6, 14. 15,</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Loue to our brethren, yea towards our enemies, and zeale of affection to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere.</p>
               <p>And after prayer, 1. Wée muſt bée <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal,</hi> 18, 21,</note> thankefull for grace.</p>
               <p>Watchfull ouer our affections to better <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>peſ,</hi> 6. 18, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om,</hi> 8, 25,</note> our obedience after, and patiently to tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the Lords leaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Theſe being obſerued before, in and after prayer: tell me how many parts be there of prayer?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thrée parts: Confeſſion of ſinne, Petition for mercy and grace, thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for bleſſings receaued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>How many parts be there of the Lords prayer?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two parts; firſt of thoſe which concerne Gods glory, ſecondly of things concerning our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>Which be thoſe that concerne God?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Preface, and the thrée firſt Petitions, ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen, hallowed by the name, thy kingdome come. Thy will be done. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concluding with <hi>Kingdome, Power, and Glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16722:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What vnderſtand you by the Preface,</hi> Our Father which art in Heauen?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That <hi>Iehouah</hi> our God, <hi>Iehouah</hi> the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Marke</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 29.</note> one, and become our Father by the death and mediation of Chriſt his Son, in whoſe name, if wée approach vnto him with faith <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 7 &amp; 16. 27.</note> and reuerence, he will make manifeſt that he is both willing and able to heare and helpe vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What more?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That <hi>being in Heauen,</hi> hée requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of vs heauenly mindes and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to worſhip him in ſpirit and truth, without any ſuperſtition, of repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 24. 25.</note> or wil-worſhip according to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reaſon, as it is forbidden in the firſt and ſecond Commandements of the firſt Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. <hi>What vnderſtand you by the firſt Petition,</hi> Hallowed be thy name?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That the glorious names and attributes of God; his wiſedome, power, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> 99. 3. <hi>Exodus,</hi> 34. 6. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 138. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 145. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> word, mercy, iuſtice, and workes, may be honored and ſanctified of vs in our thoughts, words and workes, which is the end of our creation and redemption: the contrary whereof is forbidden in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16722:15"/> third commandement of the firſt Table: <hi>thou ſhalt not take the name of thy God in vaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>2 <hi>Q. <hi>What by the ſecond,</hi> Thy kingdome come?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That righteouſnes, peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, may be increaſed in vs by <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan,</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 33. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 145. 11, 12, 13.</note> the regiment of his Word and Spirit, that Chriſt may raigne and dwell in our hearts by faith driuing out all aduerſarie power of ſinne and darknes, that being his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſubiects in the kingdome of grace, we may ſpeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly be fitted and ſuted with all his Elect in the kingdome of glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>3 <hi>Q. <hi>What by the third,</hi> Thy will be done?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God would ſubdue in vs by his grace, all things repugnant to his word &amp; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2.</note> will; that with all holy deſire, diligence and integrity (reſembling his holy angels in heauen) we may do his will, as in his word he hath manifeſted it vnto vs, being the perfect rule of faith and obedience: for the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 9. 10. 1 <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter</hi> 4. 2.</note> honor and hollowing of his name, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, increaſe, and accompliſhment of his kingdome, are vnited to the doing of his will according to his word.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>By this wee may ſee that theſe three Petitions anſwere to the foure firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16722:15"/> 
                     <hi>of the firſt Table,</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea, for in them we learne our duty to God, as concerning his worſhip, faith, feare and loue, which in this wee pray fer grace to practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>4 <hi>Q. <hi>What vnderſtand you by the ſecond parts of this prayer, and namely the fourth Petition,</hi> Giue vs this day our dayly bread?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God would vouchſafe to giue vs all ſuch things as are needfull for vs, and the place where we liue, that we may liue without deſtreſſe of minde and pride of hart, that honoring our Superiours and Parents, we may liue a peaceable life in all godlynes and honeſty, abandoning all exceſſiue care for earthly things, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 24. 25. <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. 6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 8.</note> with ſufficient, obtained by our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labors; that ſo it may go well with vs as it is promiſed in the firſt Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſecond Table, where it is ſaid, Honor thy father and thy mother, that it may go well with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>5 <hi>Q. <hi>What by the fifth Petition in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of this prayer;</hi> Forgiue vs our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That confeſſion of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnes muſt goe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 28. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> before remiſſion, becauſe they ſeperate vs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16722:16"/> from God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till they haue found free pardo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through faith in the merits of Chriſt the Mediator of the new Couenant, who hath made reconciliation for ſinne, and purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24.</note> euerlaſting righteouſnes: therefore for his ſake we deſire mercy for our ſinnes, and the puniſhments due to bee remoued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6. 7.</note> they are pledges of Gods fauour, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himſelfe to be our God and Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Why is this reaſon added,</hi> As wee do forgiue others that treſpaſſe againſt vs?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Leſt we ſhould preſume to aſke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of God, except we be free from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 14. 15. <hi>Marke</hi> 11. 25 26.</note> and malice, as it is ſaid, <hi>If yee forgiue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, God will forgiue you:</hi> therefore we pray that God who is infinite in mercies, would pardon vs, for we being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wretched ſinners, hauing not one drop of grace, yet through his grace are willing to forgiue others that <note place="margin">Prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b.</note> offend vs: For if it be the glory of a man to paſſe by infirmities, much more of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What learne you by the laſt Petition,</hi> And leade vs not into temptation?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the former Petition wee deſired pardon for ſinnes paſt, and heere wee pray for grace to reſiſt ſin in time to come, that we may be ſupported and preſerued in that <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 41.</note> ſtate of grace, whereunto wée are reſtored
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16722:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd called by Chriſt. Therefore wée pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we be not hardned with the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 40. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1. 16.</note> of ſinne, nor lead into ouer-hard tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls, againſt which our weakenes is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſiſt. but that with the temptation <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 10. 13.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he would giue the iſſue, for his glory, and our good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What vnderſtand you by this,</hi> But de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from euill?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is from the diuell the author of al <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 8.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uill, for we pray not ſimplie againſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation but againſt the euill of temptation, that wee may haue grace and ſtrength to tread Sathan, ſinne, &amp; all aduerſarie power <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 3, 4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 15.</note> oppoſing it ſelfe to our ſaluation vnder feet, through our Lord Ieſus, the ſéed of the woman, who hath already triumphed ouer them, and by whome wée hope and aſſure our ſelues we ſhall be perfect in his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What vnderſtand you by the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> For thine is the Kingdome, the Power and Glory for euer and euer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſumme of all contained in the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 17.</note> reſt: becauſe he is the immortall King inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and Almighty, God only wiſe; wee <note place="margin">1. Kingdome.</note> pray to ſerue him as his ſubiects in this <note place="margin">1. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. 5.</note> life (for the ſoueraignty of heauen &amp; earth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16722:17"/> is his) and to bee preſerued by his powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Power.</hi>
                  </note> through faith vnto the life to come, for he is all ſufficient to performe: that hée would glorifie his great name by all theſe means<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for all glory, honor, and praiſe is due t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Glorie. Pſalme</hi> 145. 11. 12.</note> him in Chriſt Ieſus for euermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Then the beginning and end of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> prayers ought to be the praiſe and glorie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, for he is not worthy to receiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> new benefits, who will not be thankefull <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 2.</note> for former receiued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Why conclude you with</hi> Amen?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew our earneſt deſire and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hope to obtaine our lawfull requeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through Chriſt the faithfull and true wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 14.</note> in whom all the promiſes of God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>yea &amp; Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Then belike theſe three laſt Petition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> anſwere to the ſixe laſt precepts of the te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Commandements of the ſecond Table of the Law.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea verily, for in them we learn ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dutie towards men: and héere we pray fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12 13.</note> grace to practiſe them that wée may liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peaceable life in all godlines and honeſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till wée bée fitted and ready for the life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come in heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16722:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Are we ſure to be heard, praying ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe rules?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes certainly, as the Scriptures of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 138. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 145. 18. 19</note> God do abundantly teach vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>But wee ſee God doth not alwayes graunt the Petitions of his children.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is, becauſe God hath otherwiſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14. 14. 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135. 6. <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 2. 2 3 4</note> firſt decréed with him ſelf; ſecondly becauſe they aske amiſſe; thirdly becauſe in his profound wiſdome he ſéeth it not good for them, fourthly becauſe he trieth their faith, loue, patience, and conſtancie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Tell me now what is a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pſal.</hi> 33. 10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 7. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                  </note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſeale of that righteouſnes which is giuen by faith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merits of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>How many ſeales or Sacraments of that kinde hath God left vnto his Church?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> But two Sacraments of the new <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 1, 2 3.</note> Couenant, as there were but two in the old, figuring righteouſnes giuen by faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Which be they?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper. anſwerable to Circumciſion, &amp; the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10, 16.</note> and ſuccéeding in their places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>How many parts be there of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, the outward ſigne, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">1 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et.</hi> 3. 21.</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16722:18"/> grace ſignified. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What is the outward ſigne in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Water, accompanied with the Word <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 28. 19.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What the inward grace ſignified?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The waſhing away of ſinne by faith in the blood of Chriſt: and the reuiuing and ſanctifying vnto true righteouſnes by his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 22. 16. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 5.</note> ſpirit, ſealing vnto the heart the aſſurance of fra forgiuenes of ſins by Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What further vſe and end hath Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To expreſſe that wée are admitted and incorporated into the houſe of God his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 9. 1. <hi>pet.</hi> 3. 20, 21. <hi>Geniſ.</hi> 17. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Church, whereof the Arke was a figure, and receaued into the Couenant of grace, heretofore figured in the ſeale of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What doth God promiſe vnto vs in this Couenant of Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt Ieſus with all the benefits of his death, buriall, reſurrection and aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 3. 21.</note> to the full aſſurance of the frée for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes, to iuſtification and life eternall</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What is the condition that the partie baptiſed is to keepe and performe?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To repent and beleeue, that is, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16722:18"/> and forſake ſinne, Satan, the world <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke</hi> 1. 4. 1. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1. 7.</note> and all the workes of the fleſh, and to liue in holines and righteouſnes according to the Spirit, beginning his new birth and life in God, to die to ſinne, and riſe vp vnto <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 3. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> righteouſnes of conuerſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Why are Infants baptiſed, which can make no confeſſion of faith &amp; repentance?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are the ſéed of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and within the outward couenant, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom belong the promiſes of grace: and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 12. 26. <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 14.</note> of ſuch is the kingdome of heauen, though not of all; but wée muſt leaue the hidden things to God, the reuealed are for vs and our children to do them. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 29<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What be the outward ſignes in the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Bread and wine, according to our Sauiours inſtitution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q <hi>Which be the inward graces ſignified and ſealed vnto vs by them?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The bodie and blood of Chriſt Ieſus, our Paſchall Lambe without blemiſh offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 26. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18. 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 25.</note> for vs, working full redemption and iuſtification for all true beleeuers, ſealing vnto them his righteouſnes to be theirs by frée imputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What further vſe hath the Lords Sups<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16722:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> To teach vs that our Couenant in Baptiſme may be renewed, and our faith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26</note> hope and loue, may be ſtrengthened and increaſed by kéeping a continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his bleſſed paſſion and death, vntill his glorious comming againe to iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q, <hi>Who ought to receiue them, and how ſhould they be prepared thereunto?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The faithfull repentant beléeuers, who only are circumciſed in heart, iudging and duly examining themſelues, whether <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 11. 28</note> they haue faith vnfained, true repentance, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</note> ſincere loue and thankfull hearts for all Gods bleſſings, eſpecially for theſe ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>pſal.</hi> 103. 1. 2.</note> mercies in Chriſt, the roote of all the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Q To what end ſerueth this knowledge of God, whereof we haue ſo briefly entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the law, faith, praiers and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To bring vs to the ſoueraigne good and end of our faith, hope and wiſhed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres; euen the ſaluation of our ſoules and bodies through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Q. What is that ſoueraigne good and ſaluation you meane?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God the author and fountaine of all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16722:19"/> goodnes: Creator, Gouernor, Redeemer, <note place="margin">2. <hi>pet.</hi> 3. 3. 4.</note> Iuſtifier, Sanctifier and Sauiour of man, who in this life hath not only giuen vs life, mouing and being, but grace through faith, working by loue to partake of his diuine nature, and begin the life of God heere, which in the life to come ſhall be perfect <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 11.</note> with him in glory for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What ſhall be the ſtate of thoſe which haue knowne and beleeued vnfainedly in the Lord?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall firſt haue their lot in the bleſſed reſurrection, to meete the Lord in <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſs.</hi> 4. 16</note> glory, and to enioy his bleſſed preſence, and fulnes of ioy, and perfect bleſſednes which no eie hath ſeene eare hath heard, or heart <note place="margin">Corinth.</note> can conceiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>What ſhall the ſtate of the wicked and ignorant vnbeleeuers bee in the world to come?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall alſo be raiſed vp to ſhame <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 2. 2. <hi>Theſſ</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7. 8. 9. 2. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et.</hi> 3. 7. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 11.</note> and euerlaſting wofulnes, puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition and paine vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, in fire vnquenchable before the throne of God, whom they ſhall neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with comfort, nor the glory of his power with ioy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16722:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>Shall this weake, mortall, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptable body of Gods Saints, be partaker with the immortall Soule, of euerlaſting lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and glory?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea, for this mortall ſhall put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, incorruption, power and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> glory, like vnto the glorious bodie of Chriſt, to ſee him as he is, and for euer and euer to be with him in glory in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where wée ſhall in perfect holineſſe <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 17</note> worſhip him all in all, to whom the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels do euer giue due worſhip: ſaying, <hi>Amen, Praiſe, and Glory, and Wiſdome, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Thankes, and Honor, and Power, and Might, be vnto our God for euermore, Amen. <hi>Finis.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>ANOTHER PRAYER TO BE vſed after Catech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſing the Children.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Gratious God, wee bleſſe and praiſe thy holy name for all thy mercies: and namely for the vſe of thy Word, now and alwayes heretofore; beſeeching thee, O Lord, to pardon our ſinnes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efects, in ſpeaking and hearing thereof, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to graunt thy bleſſing vnto vs, that as we heare to learne: ſo wee may learne to beleeue, and practiſe that which wee beleeue, to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16722:20"/> 
                  <hi>to the further conforming and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vs vnto thee, in that aſſured hope of that glory, which thou haſt prepared for all thine elect and faithfull children in the world to come, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Sauiour, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>TO THE GODLY PARENTS, Maſters and ouerſeers for Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of youth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NAture is beſt adorned with Religion and nurture: for as religion informeth the minde; ſo narture reformeth the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And as the fertilleſt ſoyle without manuring will ſoon ouergrow with weeds, ſo the apteſt wits without education, will ſoone corrupt in manners. An vnmanaged Colt will be wilde, and a childe left at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty will grow wilfull. And as the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in children and youth, vnto vice and euill are many; ſo the care and indeuour in elders to reſtraine and amend them ſhould abound: Parents by nature ſhould, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by charge ought, Magiſtrates by law, neighbours of loue and curteſie, and all men of common humanity, for maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſtian loue and piety, ciuill ſociety,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:16722:21"/> and godly policie: that the wickednes of youth bee not imputed to the remiſnes of the aged, and both puniſhed with old <hi>Elies</hi> corrections. From which the Lord keepe vs, and giue vs all grace and knowledge in all things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teach a child in the trade of his waies, and when he is old he will keep it.</hi> Prou. 22.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rules">
               <head>CERTAINE BRIEFE AND effectuall Rules for life and Conuerſation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and firſt of behauiour in the morning.</head>
               <p>FIrſt in the morning thinke vpon God, and remember thy Creator in thy youth, in the prime of thy daies, and in the ſpring of the morning; and know that he hath ſaid; <hi>My ſonne giue me thy heart;</hi> let him haue the firſt place, in thy thoughts, words and actions, lifting vp thy heart and hands with humble minde and voyce vnto him.</p>
               <p>And if time permit, let ſome good praier be ſaid of thee, or ſome other; crauing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for thy ſins in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, and for his ſake, praying for all things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thee, for the ſtate and place thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt in: with the parties from whom thou
<pb facs="tcp:16722:21"/> receiueſt mainteinance, education and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: and if thou haſt not leaſure to pray thus, yet let the Lords prayer feelingly and with deuout reuerence be ſaid of thee; let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy minde and voice ioyne and conſent together, thinking on him only vnto whom thou doeſt pray.</p>
               <p>See thou remember to vſe and frequent theſe exerciſes of prayer, at morning and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening; at meate time and other appointed; ſo ſhall the continuall vſe put thee in minde that thou forget it not.</p>
               <p>Remember that the ten Commandements of God be repeated and ſaid of thee, once in the day at the leaſt, that ſo the continuall vſe thereof, may put thee in minde of thy dutie towards God, and lead thee to Chriſt for grace.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Articles of faith, ſee thou vſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently to repeate; praying for grace, to beleeue with the heart, that which thou confeſſeſt with thy mouth, that thou maiſt increaſe in faith, hope and loue, without which thou canſt not be ſaued.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>With prayer to God do thou begin:</l>
                  <l>That he may keepe thee from all ſin.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb facs="tcp:16722:22"/>
               <head>WHFN THOV APPAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relleſt thy ſelfe.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SEE that thy cloathes and apparrell bee cleane from head to foote; decently and comly put on, tied, pointed, and pinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Delight in decent cleanlynes, neatnes and comlines in the body and garments; ſo ſhall it make thee gratefull in company, and loued of the beſt; if otherwiſe, loathed and not regarded: for by the faſhion and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the apparrell, may bee iudged the quality of the minde.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thy head, ſee thou combe and rubbe, at the leaſt thriſe in the weeke, keeping it cleane, from that which may annoy or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit thee.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Thy hands and face waſh alſo, for that is both wholeſome and hanſome.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Thy bed ſee thou decently turne vp vntill thou be ready to make it, which ſee it be well and hanſomely done, for therein thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe to differ from a beaſt.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Neate and cleanlie ſee thou be;</l>
                  <l>As is befitting thy degree.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb facs="tcp:16722:22"/>
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR TO Schoole-ward.</head>
               <p>BEing apparrelled and thy prayers ſaid, and other things performed according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, repaire without delay or loytering, vnto the ſchoole, or other buſines appointed or belonging vnto thee, vſing all diligence, and faithfulnes therein.</p>
               <p>By the way go ſoberly, orderly, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly: ſalute thy elders and betters with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent regard, and good words of the time of the day; and thy familiars and fellowes friendly with ſuch diuerſity of reuerence &amp; curteous behauiour, as is befitting to the dignity and condition of the perſons: for nothing gaineth ſo much with ſo little coſt, as humilitie and curteſie doth.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Humilitie and curteſie,</l>
                  <l>Are ſignes of grace and pietie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>Remembrances.</head>
               <p>FOrget not thy bookes, pennor, incke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, pennes, paper, &amp; all other things fit; keepe them ſafe, cleane and plaine from tearing, loſing, blotting or ſoyling, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb facs="tcp:16722:23"/>
               <head>OF BEHA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IOR AT Schoole.</head>
               <p>BEing in Schoole play not, laugh not, vſe no vncomely geſture, nor vndecent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour in ſpeech or ſigne; but humblie and carefully ſubmit thy ſelfe to obey, and learn thoſe good letters and ſciences, there inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored to be taught thee, that learning to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey in youth, thou maieſt knowe how to teach and gouerne in age; and remember that a diligent youth maketh a learned age; a ioyfull life, &amp; bleſſed death; for there is no gaine without paine, no treaſure without trauell, nor learning without labour: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhew thy ſelfe to thy Maiſter diligent and carefull to learne, coueting the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of ſuch as are better learned then thy ſelfe: contend with none but for learning, learne diligently and retaine faithfully, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe painefully, and be aſhamed to be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, but ſtriue to get before others: be not dogged and ſullen when thou art cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, reioyce when thou art praiſed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to thy ſelfe great things by thy paines, and feare correction.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Paines in youth brings honor in age:</l>
                  <l>But idlenes doth euill preſage.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb facs="tcp:16722:23"/>
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR HOME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</head>
               <p>REturning from Schoole, let thy behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our bee ſuch as may giue grace and countenance, to the place from whence thou cameſt, &amp; credit to the perſons, which haue the teaching and educating of thee.</p>
               <p>If any meete thee that are thy betters or elders, giue them the wall, and vpper hand, vailing thy bonnet reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly; for the tongue is the interpreter of the minde, and manners the image of mankind; therefore if any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion be demaunded of thee, anſwere with the like modeſtie with thy head bare, and thy countenance ſad, not ſowre and ſullain, iearing and laughing, but with a modeſt and cheerefull countenance ſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and looking them in the face ſoberly; not turning and winding like a foole, not trifeling and fumbling with the fingers like an Ape, nor lifting vp the legge like a gooſe; remembring that humility and lowlines of minde obtaineth the fauour of God, and gentle ſpeech and curteous behauiour win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the hearts of men.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dutie, meekenes, thankes and loue,</l>
                  <l>Are vertues ſprung from God aboue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb facs="tcp:16722:24"/>
               <head>OF BEHA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IOVR AT home, at the Table.</head>
               <p>BEing come home, vſe all reuerent dutie and obedience to thy parents and el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as becommeth thee; and ſe thou come not into the hall, or in their ſight, vndecent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnmannerly, with thy hoſe vngarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, thy ſhooes foule, broken or vntied; thy coate vnbuttoned, vnpointed, torne, or vncleane; thy hands and face vnwaſhed, &amp; filthie: but comely and reuerently, ſee thou approach into their ſight, as in the preſence of God, whoſe inſtruments for thy good they are, and whoſe bleſſings thou commeſt now to receiue, for the ſuſtentation of thy naturall life; and forget not to pray vnto, and praiſe the Lord of life, by whom wee liue, moue and haue our being.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be not like the filthie ſwine,</l>
                  <l>But pray to God before thou dine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR WHEN ANY part of Scripture is read.</head>
               <p>IF there bee any exerciſe of reading and hearing Gods word and prayer, before mcale or after, or at the time of refection,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16722:24"/> ſee that with all meekenes and reuerence, with deuout attention &amp; loue, thou marke the ſenſe and matter of that which is read, as well as the words, ſo ſhalt thou inrich thy minde and wit with true wiſedome, and thy tongue with gratious words.</p>
               <p>See that with like deuotion and reuerence thou behaue thy ſelfe, in time of prayer and grace, lifting vp thy heart &amp; hands to God, during the time, thinking vpon him in heauen, vpon whom thou doeſt call heere on earth; and know that he is a conſuming fire, and will not be mocked.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Being at exerciſe diuine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe reuerence in ſuch a time.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>Of behauiour at meale time.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHen thou feedeſt, vſe mannerly modeſtie and modeſt ſobriety; moderately and temperately eating and drinking that which is appointed for thee, without greedineſſe and exceſſe, that after thy meat, thy wit and minde may be freſher and not duller, and thy body more liuely, and not heauier and vnapt to ſtudy, &amp;c.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Many thouſands their death doe eate:</l>
                  <l>When few haue died for lacke of meate.</l>
               </lg>
               <p n="2">2. Let thy talke be little and ſparing, except
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16722:25"/> when iuſt occaſion be offered, or queſtion asked, and then ſpeake or anſwere aptly &amp; diſtinctly; thinke before thou ſpeake, and ſpeake ſoberly and truly; if thy betters aske thee a queſtion, anſwere them reuerently; and thy fellowes and equalles curteouſly, without biting taunts or loud vnreuerent words. Take thy meate without ſnatching, for that is dog-like; and doe not murmure or grudge, for that is ſwine-like: be not the firſt in the diſh, nor the laſt ſufficed; for that is a token of a greedy &amp; vnſatiable deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, eſpecially eſchew exceſſe in drinking.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>More with drinke their bellies burſt</l>
                  <l>Then euer yet haue died of thurſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>With thankefull minde and contented heart, receaue that which is prepared for thee, &amp; reuerently riſe as thou ſateſt downe with giuing of thankes to God.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be not like a fooliſh Aſſe,</l>
                  <l>But giue God thankes before thou paſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR ON THE Sabbath day.</head>
               <p>THink on the Lords day the day before, and make an end if poſſible thou maieſt of all ſuch things &amp; buſineſſes as ſhould
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16722:25"/> any way hinder that daies exerciſe, of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, ſpeaking or meditating of Gods Word and workes.</p>
               <div n="1" type="rule">
                  <head>1. <hi>Of Preparation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the morning early prepare thee to riſe vp in mind &amp; body, to ſerue God the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and the Son our Sauiour, through the grace of the ſanctifying ſpirit of grace, ſhunning and hating all ſinne and euill, in thoughts, words, and deedes, as thou art commanded to ſanctifie and keepe holy the Sabbath day; not doing thine owne will, not ſpeaking vaine words, nor thinking euill thoughts; but let thy will be led to do the will of God heere in earth as it is in heauen; and let thy minde cary vp thy thoughts to meditate on the creation of all by almighty God, of the redemption of all by our bleſſed Sauiour, who is our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, righteouſnes and eternall reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="rule">
                  <head>2. <hi>In the Church.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>And when thou commeſt into the Church or congregation aſſembled in the name of God to heare his word, and to pray and cal vpon his name; know that thou art in the preſence of the eternall God and his holy Angels, who not only ſeeth thee and thy behauiour, but alſo vnderſtandeth thy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16722:26"/> thoughts and ſecret motions; ſee therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy geſture be comely.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="rule">
                  <head>3. <hi>Of Hearing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>And thy behauiour reuerent, giuing due regard with meekenes vnto the word of God, that the ſenſe and ſubſtance thereof may enter into thy mind, as the ſound doth pierce thy eare; for it is the power of God, to ſaue thy ſoule, if thou ſo heare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine it; or elſe it is the ſauor of death vnto death, vnto thy eternall damnation, with the Diuell and his Angels, if thou doeſt careleſſely neglect, contemne &amp; deſpiſe it: but if thou be carefull to marke what ſinne is reproued, and flye the ſame; and what vertue is commended, and embrace th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſame, it ſhall then amend thy memory, and manners to grow in knowledge, to learne to liue and die as a Chriſtian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="rule">
                  <head>4. <hi>Of Praying.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the time of prayer, thy body muſt bee humble and caſt downe vpon thy knees, meekly and reuerently lifting vp thy hands and heart vnto God in heauen; ioyning with them that ſpeake in praier, to ſay with them as occaſion is, or to lift vp thy minde with audible and good voice and harty affection, ſaying <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16722:26"/>
                  <p> And remember that it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoeuer calleth vpon the name of the Lord, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from iniquitie ſhall be ſaued:</hi> but whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth not, it is an euident token of a wicked and vngodly minde, as it is ſaid <hi>The wicked call not vpon the Lord,</hi> and therefore there is no faith, no hope, no ſaluation, for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="rule">
                  <head>5. <hi>Of the articles of the faith.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>When the Articles of faith be repeated, thou muſt with like reuerence &amp; affection, either ſtanding or kneeling, pronounce it audibly and diſtinctly; for as thou beleeueſt with thy heart, ſo muſt thou confeſſe with thy mouth vnto ſaluation, remembring alwayes to ioyne with the reſt, in ſaying <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="rule">
                  <head>6. <hi>Of the ten Commandements.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>When the ten Commandements are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated and ſaid, heare them with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and feare, conſidering in euery one thy ſin and defects, praying for mercy and grace, through Chriſt Ieſus, to endeuour all thy heart to keepe them; and then that which thou canſt not doe, he wil performe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="rule">
                  <head>7. <hi>Of ſinging Pſalmes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Likewiſe when Pſalmes and praiſes to God are ſinging, vſe all care and reuerence
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16722:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> in ſinging with a grace and affectionate heart, keeping tune and time orderly, to the praiſe of the God of order.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="rule">
                  <head>8. <hi>Not to goe away.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Remember thou gad not in and out of the Church and Congregation, at thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; for that is vngodly, vnſeemely, and verie offenſiue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="rule">
                  <head>9. <hi>Not to prate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Neither vſe to prattle, or priuatly to reade or thinke of matters, not pertaining to the place and worke in hand; for that is to offer the ſacrifice of fooles. Tarie vntill all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God be performed, and the bleſſing pronounced, leſt thou ſhew thy ſelfe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner of holy things, and one vnworthy to be partaker thereof; as <hi>Iudas</hi> was, who made more haſt then good ſpeede, and ſped accordingly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="rule">
                  <head>10. <hi>Practiſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Returning out, vſe like reuerent behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and thinke often vpon that which out of Gods word thou haſt heard; to practiſe it in thy behauiour; and know, that practiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd of faith and knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16722:27"/> the hearers of the word, but the doers of the will of God ſhall be ſaued.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Sabbath ſee thou ſanctifie,</l>
                     <l>Auoyding all impietie.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR IN TIME of recreation and play.</head>
               <p>VSE ſuch exerciſes of bodie as are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence and perill either to thy ſelfe or others, either in bones or ioynts, name or eſtimation; that it may be ſuch as fitte beſt for thy minde to increaſe in good lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and for thy body, for health and ſtrength: remembring there is a time of paſtime and mirth, (as the wiſe man ſaith) but take heed it be done in due time and meaſure: as he alſo counſelleth, ſaying, <hi>If thou finde hony, eate thereof; but eate not too much;</hi> for the exceſſe of euery thing is ſinne, therefore exceed not in loſſe of time, but ſee thou redeeme it with the loſſe of pleaſure, &amp; thou ſhalt finde increaſe of greater profit.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vſe paſtime and pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>In due time and meaſure.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16722:28"/>
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR AT night.</head>
               <p n="1">1 AT night when all the duties of the day are ended, and that the time of reſt is come, approach quietly and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly into thy ward and place of reſt appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inted; and then with due reuerence addreſſe thee, to the reuerent hearing and reading of the word of God, according as the nightly exerciſes require; if it be in ſinging of Pſalmes, ſee that it be done alſo reuerently with due regard of the matter as well as the method, and melodie, which muſt alſo be regarded, as we are by God commanded to ſing with feeling and a grace in the heart, with vnderſtanding and skil in due marking and keeping the time and tune, for the God of order delighteth in concord and harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and hateth confuſion and diſcord, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in his ſpeciall ſeruices. Therefore ſing reuerently, orderly and deuoutly, keeping time and tune; ſo ſhall it pleaſe God, and be comended of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Theſe ended, commit thy ſelfe into the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16722:28"/> tuition of God by prayer, remembring wherein thou haſt faulted or failed of thy duty, to call for mercy, &amp; wherein through grace thou haſt performed or deſired any good, to be thankefull vnto him that is the fountaine and giuer of all goodnes.</p>
               <p n="3">3 See thy hoſe and ſhooes be cleane, and thy cloathes decently laid vp, readily of thee to be found in the morning when thou ſhalt riſe to put them on.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>To bed ſee that thou goe in time,</l>
                  <l>And riſe likewiſe, the gaine is thine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>OF BEHAVIOVR ABROAD in ſeruice.</head>
               <p>VVHEN thou art abroad in ſeruice remember and practiſe diligently the counſell of God, which ſaith, <hi>Seruants,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>be obedient and ſubiect vnto them that are your maſters, and pleaſe them in all things good and lawfull</hi> (for otherwiſe, better it is to obey God then man) <hi>not with eie-ſeruice, as men pleaſers, but in ſinglenes of hart fearing God; and whatſoeuer you do, do it hartily as to the Lord, and not vnto men; knowing that of the Lord you ſhall receaue the reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16722:29"/>
               <p> Therefore, ſaith he, be not anſwerers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2. 9.</note> nor ſaucy, be not pickers nor purloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but ſhew all good faithfulnes, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diligence as vnto thy father, yea as vnto the Lord himſelfe, who ſerued for vs, a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to all, that hee might wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne all from ſlauery, and ſeruice of ſin &amp; Sathan. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber among many, the duties of thy calling, as thou art a ſeruant; theſe foure eſpeciallie are required of thee. Firſt, faithfulnes voide of fraud, and filthy flattery; Secondly, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence void of ſloth and grudging; Thirdly, to ſeeke and procure their profit and good, before thine own profit or pleaſure; Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be ſilent and ſecret, not anſwering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine rudely and ſaucily, nor reuealing their ſecrets abroad; therefore it is wittily ſaid by one, that a good ſeruant ſhould haue the back of an Aſſe to beare patiently; the ſnout of a Swine to feed homely; the tongue of a ſheepe to keepe ſilence gently. Or thus, To haue large eares to heare readilie, a ſhort tongue, ſpeaking ſeldome; and truly light feete, ſwift in ſeruice and meſſage; &amp; cleane hands void of pilfering and couſenage.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Take pains in youth while ſtrength doſt laſt,</l>
                  <l>Then reſt in age when health is paſt.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:16722:29"/>
                  <l> Be loath to offen, be diligent to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Be willing to amend, of ſufferance comes eaſe.</l>
                  <l>Good paine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> breedeth honor, true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertue getteth fame,</l>
                  <l>Sloth bringeth miſerie, and vice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ternall ſhame.</l>
                  <l>A youth void of induſtrie,</l>
                  <l>An age void of honeſtie.</l>
                  <l>Where vice in youth doth beare the ſway,</l>
                  <l>There vertues will in age decay.</l>
                  <l>A youth well inſtructed,</l>
                  <l>Makes an age wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſpoſed.</l>
                  <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that in youth, by reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> guides his daies,</l>
                  <l>In age ſhall keepe his footſteps from decayes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>SHORT SAYINGS FOR FVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruction of dutie towards <hi>God and man.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <head>1. <hi>Towards God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>LEarne to know God in his word.</item>
                  <item>Beleeue in God and his promiſes.</item>
                  <item>Feare God in his iudgements.</item>
                  <item>Loue God in his mercies.</item>
                  <item>Pray to him for grace.</item>
                  <item>Praiſe him for his goodnes.</item>
                  <item>Reade and heare his Word diligently.</item>
                  <item>Loue and reuerence his Miniſters.</item>
                  <item>Frequent the places of prayer.</item>
                  <item>Be careful often to heare the word preached</item>
                  <item>Quench not the ſpirit diſpiſe not propheſing</item>
                  <item>Feare God &amp; keepe his Commandements.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>2. <hi>Towards our Superiours.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Honor the King.</item>
                  <item>Obey good lawes.</item>
                  <item>Loue reuerence, &amp; pray for the Magiſtrates,</item>
                  <item>Pay all duties to thy power.</item>
                  <item>Speake well of them in authoritie.</item>
                  <item>If they be good, thanke God for them.</item>
                  <item>If they be euill, pray for their amendement.</item>
                  <item>Princes are as the glaſſe, the ſchoole the booke, where ſubiects eies, do reade, do learne, do looke Kings on earth are Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of God in heauen,</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>3. <hi>Towards our Parents.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Honor thy Parents.</item>
                  <item>Reuerence their good counſell.</item>
                  <item>Obey their good Commandements.</item>
                  <item>Be ſubiect to their corrections.</item>
                  <item>Be humble, reuerent, and dutifull to them.</item>
                  <item>By good behauiour make them glad.</item>
                  <item>By ill demeanor make them not ſad.</item>
                  <item>Deſerue and ſeeke for their bleſſing.</item>
                  <item>Deſerue not their curſe.</item>
                  <item>Pray daily for them.</item>
                  <item>Releeue them if they be in want.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>4. <hi>Towards the aged.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Reuerence the aged.</item>
                  <item>Be dutifull to thy betters.</item>
                  <item>Be humble and lowly to them.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:30"/>
                  <item> Be kinde and curteous to all.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>5. <hi>Of familiaritie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Be friendly and familiar with the good.</item>
                  <item>Keepe no company with the euill.</item>
                  <item>Try before thou truſt.</item>
                  <item>Hinder no mans good name.</item>
                  <item>Reioyce not in anothers croſſe.</item>
                  <item>Beare with others infirmities, that others may beare with thee.</item>
                  <item>Reioyce with thoſe that reioyce.</item>
                  <item>Mourne with them that mourne.</item>
                  <item>Be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle &amp; curteous to al, offenſiue to none.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Of Anger.</head>
                  <item>Be angrie againſt ſin, but ſin not.</item>
                  <item>Appeaſe debate, abſteine from hate.</item>
                  <item>If anger ariſe, let not ſin ſurpriſe.</item>
                  <item>Be not hard to be appeaſed.</item>
                  <item>Be mercifull and pitifull.</item>
                  <item>Be gentle and courteous.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>6. <hi>Of Speech.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Be ſlow to ſpeake, eſpecially euill.</item>
                  <item>Be ſwift to heare good things.</item>
                  <item>Thinke before thou ſpeake.</item>
                  <item>Speake aduiſedly and truly.</item>
                  <item>Speake not vainely and skurrillouſly.</item>
                  <item>Anſwere aptly and mannerly.</item>
                  <item>Keepe counſell committed vnto thee.</item>
                  <item>Reueale not thy maſters ſecrets.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:31"/>
                  <item> Reueale not thine owne to euery friend.</item>
                  <item>Promiſe aduiſedly.</item>
                  <item>pay thy debts truly.</item>
                  <item>Performe conſtantly.</item>
                  <item>Be not raſh and foole-hardie.</item>
                  <item>Be not wiſe in thine owne conceipt.</item>
                  <item>Be not arrogant.</item>
                  <item>Striue not with thy ouer-match.</item>
                  <item>Be at peace with vertue, &amp; warre with vice.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>7. <hi>Of learning and knowledge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Loue vertue and knowledge.</item>
                  <item>Hate vice and ignorance.</item>
                  <item>Haunt wiſe mens company.</item>
                  <item>Shunne fooliſh ſociety.</item>
                  <item>Praier, hearing, and reading, increaſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, without knowledge the mind is not good.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>8. <hi>Of thine eſtate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Maintaine thy ſelfe iuſtly.</item>
                  <item>Liue in order.</item>
                  <item>Liue within thy compaſſe.</item>
                  <item>Be content with thine eſtate.</item>
                  <item>Pouerty is no hinderance to vertue.</item>
                  <item>Contented meane is greateſt wealth.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>9. <hi>Of Apparell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Be comely and cleane in thine apparell.</item>
                  <item>Be not proud and curious.</item>
                  <item>Be not ſlouenlike and rude.</item>
                  <item>Be ſober in geſture and gate.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:31"/>
                  <item> Be not idle and vaine.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>10. <hi>Of Diet.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Take heed of all exceſſe, for that is ſinne.</item>
                  <item>Be temperat in diet.</item>
                  <item>Drinke moderatly, and eate ſoberly.</item>
                  <item>Surfeting and drunkennes is a deadly ſin.</item>
                  <item>Abſtinence is good for ſoule and body.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>11. <hi>Of Recreation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Vſe moderate exerciſes.</item>
                  <item>Play not in any thing exceeding modeſtie and meaſure.</item>
                  <item>Redeeme the time and leeſe it not.</item>
                  <item>No greater loſſe then time, and nothing leſſe accounted of.</item>
                  <item>Neglected time, is follies chiefeſt ſigne.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>12. <hi>Of the end.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>The true and beſt ende of all is the feare of God.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>When vertuous daies do end they are not done:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But liue two liues, where others haue but one.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In all beginnings remember the end.</item>
                  <item>For to begin well is good, but to end well is better.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leud life is loſſe, good death felicity,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The chiefeſt gaine, the end of miſery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For that's not death to change the life and die:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But that is death, which doth all ioyes deny.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:32"/>
                  <item> 
                     <hi>Then happy he, who doth in time prepare</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To die, to liue, the end of worldly care.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The end of all things is at hand; be ſober therefore and watch vnto prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>A PRAYER TO BE SAID EVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie morning and euening by the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <hi>dren in their ſeuerall Wards.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <head>And firſt remember that.</head>
                  <item>Without knowledge the mind is not good.</item>
                  <item>Without faith no pleaſing of God.</item>
                  <item>Without nurture, no attaining to vertue.</item>
                  <item>Without praier, no hope of grace.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Therefore,</head>
                  <item>Euery one that is godly will pray in time conue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nient. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal.</hi> 34. 14. 6. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal.</hi> 31. 7. 8. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal.</hi> 14. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal.</hi> 145. 18 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal.</hi> 138. 6.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>But the wicked call not vpon God.</item>
                  <item>The Lord is nigh all them that call vpon him in truth, and faithfully.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For though the Lord be high, yet hath he reſpect vnto the lowly: As for the proud hee behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them a farre off.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall God and mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt Ieſus, we humblie beſeech thee to haue mercy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs thy poore children, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16722:32"/> pardon all our ſinnes committed againſt thy Diuine Maieſtie at any time of our life here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, either in omitting or committing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing againſt thy bleſſed word and holy will; and graunt vs thy grace, O Lord, that we may be truly repentant for them and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily thankfull vnto thee for all thy vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mercies and fauours beſtowed vpon vs, and the ſtate and place wherein we liue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee for Chriſt his ſake to continue and increaſe them euer hereafter both in ſoule and body vnto vs, and alſo to receiue vs all into thy bleſſed protection, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne, nor Sathan aſſaile or preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, to hurt the peace of our ſoules, or health of our bodies, but that being bleſſed and protected by thee, O Lord, we may be better able and more carefull, to ſerue thee in our ſeuerall places &amp; callings, to become thy faithfull ſeruants, &amp; inſtruments of thy glory, for the good of thy Church, &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale of our countrie wherin we liue. O Lord bleſſe and defend our Soueraigne King, the Queene, and the Prince their Son, with the reſt of their Royal Progenie; bleſſe his Maieſties honorable Counſellors and Nobles, &amp; direct them, &amp; all in office in the Church and State vnder him, eſpecially to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16722:33"/> aduance true religion and vertue, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſin and impiety. Continue thy mercie and protection O Lord towards theſe his Maieſties Dominions of great Britaine, and countries annexed, and thy people and Churches in them: increaſe the number of faithfull and painefull Preachers amongſt them, that ſo thy moſt holy name may be hallowed, thy kingdome inlarged, and thy bleſſed will accompliſhed in faith and loue, in verity &amp; vnity. O Lord bleſſe and defend this Citie, with the Gouernors and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, together with this houſe and whole ſocietie, and all thoſe from whom we receaue this comfortable maintenance, reliefe and godly education; increaſe thy ſpirituall graces in them, and multiplie thy temporall bleſſings vpon them, O Lord, that they neuer want will and meanes to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in performing the good workes thou haſt begun for the aduancement of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the comfort of vs and others thy poore diſtreſſed ones, &amp; the increaſe of their owne comfort in the aſſurance of thy mercy in Chriſt Ieſus. Theſe mercies and all other bleſſings needfull, O bleſſed God of grace and mercy, we pray thee to graunt vnto vs, and the reſt of thy Church, euen for Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16722:33"/>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
